<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="//purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="//purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="//www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0" xmlns:media="//search.yahoo.com/mrss/"><channel><title><![CDATA[Juan David Saab - Juan David Saab - FrontEnd & Web Developer]]></title><description><![CDATA[Thoughts, code and ideas.]]></description><link>https://juansaab.github.io/</link><image><url>https://juansaab.github.io/favicon.png</url><title>Juan David Saab - Juan David Saab - FrontEnd &amp; Web Developer</title><link>https://juansaab.github.io/</link></image><generator>Ghost 2.0</generator><lastBuildDate>Mon, 27 Aug 2018 05:26:03 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://juansaab.github.io/author/juan/rss/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><ttl>60</ttl><item><title><![CDATA[How to create your own Medium like blog on GitHub Pages using Ghost for free]]></title><description><![CDATA[I'm an assiduous reader of Medium and always loved its simple and content focused design. That's why I decided to start this blog, using GitHub pages and a local installation of Ghost.]]></description><link>https://juansaab.github.io/how-to-create-your-own-medium-like-blog-on-github-pages-using-ghost/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5b82e802b0c335085b040f8f</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Juan David Saab]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 26 Aug 2018 18:25:43 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="https://juansaab.github.io/content/images/2018/08/have-your-own-medium-blog.png" medium="image"/><content:encoded><![CDATA[<img src="https://juansaab.github.io/content/images/2018/08/have-your-own-medium-blog.png" alt="How to create your own Medium like blog on GitHub Pages using Ghost for free"><p>Working as a web developer but also as an UX designer for more than 10 years, I felt for running a blog that could focus exclusively on Code. I'm an assiduous reader of Medium and always loved its simple and content focused design. That's why I decided to start this blog, using GitHub pages and a local installation of Ghost.</p><h2 id="how-to-setup-a-github-pages-website-using-ghost-as-content-editing-platform">How to setup a GitHub pages website using Ghost as content editing platform?</h2><p>From all the alternatives to do it, i decided to have a local instance of Ghost and publishing of the static files to GitHub using Buster. Even when Buster seemed quite outdated to the time I made this installation, I found this excellent step by step tutorial which I changed just a bit to use Ghost-CLI.</p><h3 id="1-install-node-js-on-your-machine">1. Install Node.js on your machine</h3><p>If you haven't installed yet you can do it many ways, from installing the package from the official website to using HomeBrew on your Mac. As I'm a MacOS user, I handle all my packages with brew.</p><p><code>brew install node</code></p>
<p>If you don't have brew installed, you can follow this quick tutorial.</p><h3 id="2-be-sure-you-have-installed-the-node-version-required-by-ghost-cli">2. Be sure you have installed the Node version required by Ghost-CLI</h3><p>I liked the idea of using Ghost-CLI. However, it only runs on the LTS version of node (currently 8.6). In order to handle multiple versions of node on your machine you can use a package named n. You can use npm to install it</p><p><code>$ npm install n -g</code></p>
<p>Then you can install the required node version by running:</p>
<p><code>$ n 8.6</code></p>
<h3 id="3-install-the-ghost-cli-using-npm">3. Install the Ghost-CLI using npm</h3><p>Then you can install the ghost-cli using npm by running:</p><p><code>npm install ghost-cli -g</code></p>
<h3 id="4-select-a-folder-for-your-ghost-installation-and-run-the-cli-installation-script">4. Select a folder for your Ghost installation and run the CLI installation script</h3><p>In order to version the code of my ghost installation, I created a GitHub repo. After cloning on my machine I entered the folder I wanted ghost to be installed and did an:</p><p><code>ghost install local</code></p>
<p>You should see something like this:</p><figure class="kg-image-card"><img src="https://juansaab.github.io/content/images/2018/08/Install-ghost-locally-with-ghost-cli.png" class="kg-image" alt="How to create your own Medium like blog on GitHub Pages using Ghost for free"></figure><h3 id="5-create-your-account-and-enter-the-administration-panel-to-setup-your-blog">5. Create your account and enter the administration panel to setup your blog</h3><p>Once the installation is finished, you can open <a href="https://juansaab.github.io/ghost/">https://juansaab.github.io/ghost/</a> on your navigator to open the administration panel for your new blog. After creating your account you will have a nice blog with some introductory posts about how to use Ghost. If you want to delete them, you can just delete the author named Ghost from the <em>Team</em> panel.</p>]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>